# **Mathis Richter**

#### Postdoctoral Researcher

@ mathis.richter@ini.rub.de

% mathisrichter.de

Bochum, Germany

#### SUMMARY

Researcher and software engineer with expertise in neural cognitive systems; Ph.D. on the link between language and perception; published 15 peer-reviewed articles, receiving two best paper awards; co-developed a graphical C++ framework for neural modeling; two exchange years during high school (USA) and university (UK).

#### **EXPERIENCE**

#### Research Associate

### Institute for Neural Computation, Ruhr-University Bochum

- Researching how language understanding links to perceptual processes in the human brain and in artificial neural networks
- · Developing fully neural models of cognition based on dynamic field theory
- · Published 15 peer-reviewed manuscripts (journals & conferences)
- · Gave 3 oral and 4 poster presentations at international conferences
- Initiated and co-developed C++ framework cedar for neural modeling, used by the entire lab and in teaching (cedar.ini.rub.de)
- · Lead organization of 4 international summer schools with 20 participants
- Teaching (lectures, lab courses in Matlab); supervising Master students
- https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=lwAVM2QAAAAJ

#### Research Assistant

#### Institute for Neural Computation, Ruhr-University Bochum

- Designed and implemented a prototype for the framework cedar (Python)
- · Designed, and oversaw the modernization of the institute's website
- Teaching assistance (correcting exercises)

#### OTHER EXPERIENCE

#### **Machine Learning Course**

3-month course by Stanford University on Coursera (07/2019 - 10/2019).

#### Telluride Neuromorphic Cognition Engineering Workshops

3-week workshops in 2012 and 2014. Implemented dynamic neural fields in spiking neurons. Built a system to extract the direction of object motion using a neuromorphic DVS camera. Developed a neural model to control grasping movements on a NAO robot.

#### Supercomputing Internship

2-week internship with NEC High Performance Computing in 2006. Adapted open-source software (C) for use on a supercomputer.

### Bochumer GNU/Linux User Group

Founded and lead a local Linux user group with about 10 members (2005-2009). Organized installation parties, PGP key signing parties, tutorials, and small lectures in a local hacking space.

#### **EDUCATION**

# Dr.-Ing. Engineering (Ph.D. equivalent) Ruhr-University Bochum

**♥** Bochum, Germany

- Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Gregor Schöner
- · Grade: magna cum laude / very good

## M.Sc. Applied Computer Science

**Ruhr-University Bochum** 

**1** 04/2010 - 09/2011

**♀** Bochum, Germany

• Grade: 93 %

# Computer Science, Exchange Year University of Birmingham

**10/2007- 06/2008** 

₱ Birmingham, UK

## B.Sc. Applied Computer Science

Ruhr-University Bochum

**10/2004 - 09/2010** 

• Grade: 81%

#### High School Exchange Year

East Union High School

**1** 08/2007- 06/2001

Afton, IA, USA

#### AWARDS

#### Best Modeling Paper: Higher Cognition

CogSci 2016; 4 prizes on 480 accepted papers

#### **Best Paper**

ICANN 2014; 1 prize on 108 accepted papers

#### Top 5% of Class

M.Sc. Applied Computer Science, 2011

#### **TECHNOLOGIES**

C++	Python	Matlab	Git	CMake
Linux	LATEX			

#### LANGUAGES

German	Native	••••
English	Professional Proficiency	••••
French	Beginner	••••

#### A neural dynamic architecture that autonomously builds mental models

40th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society

Parthena Kounatidou, Mathis Richter, Gregor Schöner

% https://cogsci.mindmodeling.org/2018/papers/0138/index.html

#### A neural dynamic model generates descriptions of object-oriented actions

**Topics in Cognitive Science** 

Mathis Richter, Jonas Lins, Gregor Schöner

## 2017 % https://doi.org/10.1111/tops.12240

#### Developing dynamic field theory architectures for embodied cognitive systems with cedar

Frontiers in Neurorobotics

Oliver Lomp, Mathis Richter, Stephan K. U. Zibner, Gregor Schöner

% https://doi.org/10.3389/fnbot.2016.00014

#### A neural dynamic model parses object-oriented actions

38th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society

Mathis Richter, Jonas Lins, Gregor Schöner

% https://cogsci.mindmodeling.org/2016/papers/0337/index.html

Best Modeling Paper Award: Higher Cognition; lead to 2017 publication in Topics in Cognitive Science

#### A neural dynamic architecture resolves phrases about spatial relations in visual scenes

24th International Conference on Artificial Neural Networks

Mathis Richter, Jonas Lins, Sebastian Schneegans, Gregor Schöner

% https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-11179-7\_26

Best Paper Award

#### Autonomous neural dynamic to test hypotheses in a model of spatial language

36th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society

Mathis Richter, Jonas Lins, Sebastian Schneegans, Yulia Sandamirskaya, Gregor Schöner

% https://cogsci.mindmodeling.org/2014/papers/492/

#### A robotic architecture for action selection and behavioral organization inspired by human cognition

IEEE/RSJ Intl. Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems

Mathis Richter, Yulia Sandamirskaya, Gregor Schöner

## 2012 % https://doi.org/10.1109/IROS.2012.6386153

#### A neural-dynamic architecture for behavioral organization of an embodied agent

IEEE Intl. Conference on Development and Learning

Yulia Sandamirskaya, Mathis Richter, Gregor Schöner

**2011** 

% https://doi.org/10.1109/DEVLRN.2011.6037353